I already have a company insurance. Do I
have to buy a personal insurance?
Company
insurance personal insurance? I have
company insurance. Why do I need a
personal insurance? So why should I buy
a personal health insurance if I'm
already covered by my company's
insurance? Isn't it a waste of money? I
have been in the space for 20 years now
and this is the most most common
question I get wherever I go. So yes,
company insurance of course is supremely
convenient. It's easy to be enrolled.
Claims are smoother and the best part is
that it is free, but there are not one,
not two, but six serious problems in
your employer's health insurance that
you must be aware of. Let's check each
of them out one by one. Problem number
six, employee health insurance is not
permanent. Company insurance is like
free Wi-Fi in an office or in a cafe.
Once you leave, of course, the Wi-Fi
stops. Similarly, when you leave your
company, your health insurance also of
course stops. And if you are on a break
or you're starting on your own, then you
may be without a cover during this time.
But what about portability? H smart.
Wait till I explain problem number two.
And what if my new employer also
provides health insurance? Rupja, wait
till the end of the video. That takes me
to problem number five. The coverage
provided by the employer is usually
usually very low. Unlike personal
insurance, employer policies are
one-year group policies. Employers look
at insurance in the short term. They
estimate coverage that is useful for the
mass population in the company in that
given year. That's exactly why the
coverage with most companies is 3 to 5
lakhs. Now if you really know a tad bit
about hospital bills, you will know that
three to five lakhs may be good for
minor hospitalizations but may not work
for a major hospitalization especially
in a big hospital in a big city. For
instance, a claim for a heart surgery
can cost anything between three lakhs to
10 lakhs to even 15 lakhs depending on
complications, depending on city,
depending on the hospital. Problem
number four, a company health insurance
comes with many hidden terms and
conditions. Every year your HR sends you
a deck that explains the insurance cover
in simple language. The problem is that
we don't go through it till we have a
claim. Health insurance policies of even
large e-commerce players I've seen like
Amazon India large tech companies like
Infosys and TCS have limits on room rent
have co-pay conditions where you need to
pay a part of the claim from your own
pocket. That reminds me take this as
homework. Okay? Search for the health
insurance deck sent by your HR in your
email box during the weekend and let me
know what I said was true or not. Search
for terms like co-ay limits and you will
know soon. That also reminds me to
remind you to subscribe to Bashak right
now. We are working very hard to ensure
you get sharp insights and valuable tips
to use insurance smartly. You won't
regret it. That's a personal promise.
That's what takes me to problem number
three. A problem number three is that
coverage of company policies can get
downgraded over the years. I say this
from a lot of experience. Every year
your company's CFO sits with the
insurance company and negotiates pricing
for the upcoming year's health
insurance. This pricing is calculated
based on the previous year's claims. Now
if the insurer has seen a large number
of claims then either the CFO will have
to agree to pay a larger premium than
last year or what happens in most cases
they will have to reduce the benefits by
introducing limits. Now I've seen the
most fancy covers provided to employees
in a new
startup and as years go by the covers
keep degrading because of large claims.
The classic example of this is parents
insurance. Many of you may not know but
employers used to give free health
insurance to parents in early 2000s and
now because of claims employees have
asked employees to bear the premium from
their pocket. While your healthare and
your family's healthcare is yours, the
health insurance provided by your
company cannot be in your control. That
takes me to problem number two. You
cannot cannot cannot depend on the
portability promised by your company.
Yes, you are promised portability but
unfortunately the portability is not
guaranteed. As per regulations, insurers
have the right to evaluate your medical
history during portability. Just like
when you buy a fresh policy and then
decide whether to give you coverage or
not. And I've seen so many cases if you
have made a claim or have medical
history, insurers have denied
portability. You may then be at a
disadvantaged position when exploring
products. Someone without a cover but
with medical history. This is
particularly true for senior citizen
covers and top-ups purchased by you
through your employer. And now the most
important issue, problem number one,
health insurance is like a loan. You
don't get health insurance when you need
it. If you are thinking that you will
get a health insurance when you retire
or when you leave your company, remember
if you or any of your family members
have chronic diseases or any multiple
disease or disorders and you're looking
for a health insurance, then you may not
get the most comprehensive coverage that
you're looking for. What's worse, you
may actually have to pay a higher
premium for the higher risk you carry.
Ultimate ultimate hack is to pre-book
health insurance when you're young and
healthy. That's when you will get the
best most comprehensive policy with the
best most comprehensive coverage.